Guide to the New-York Historical Society Publication Editorial Records 1939-2000, 2009 NYHS-RG 17
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Publications (1940s-1960s)., 1939-1982, 2009; 24.42 Linear feet
  - Subseries I.A. General Correspondence, 1939-1982; 4.17 Linear feet
    - M. General (2 folders), 1948-1966 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-2)
      Principal correspondents include Robert M. McClung, John F. McDermott, Philip Marsh, M. Bernard Mason, James R. Masterson, Harry C.W. Melick, Emma deLong Mills, Elizabeth (Mrs. Clement C.) Moore, Katherine Prentis Murphy.
    - McClellan, George B., Jr., 1953 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence with the J.B. Lippincott Company concerning publication of the manuscript autobiography of McClellan.
    - Merritt, Arthur, 1949-1961 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
      Concerns Arthur Hastings Merritt's autobiography, his article on Parson Weems and the Washington cherry tree story, and other writings. Includes a photograph of Merritt.
    - Miller, Perry, 1957-1961 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
      Concerns attempts to have Miller review various books.
    - N. General, 1951-1965 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
      Principal correspondents include Eric P. Newman (in conection with an article by Kenneth Scott).
    - New York Past and Present, 1955-1956, 1963 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence with John Davis Hatch concerning a proposed reprint of I.N. Phelps Stokes's book.
    - New York State Historical Association, 1949-1958 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
      Primarily concerns the historical association's acquisition of N-YHS publications. 1957-58 correspondence with Dorothy Barck at the association includes references to the Dictionary of Artists in America.
    - O. General, 1953-1954 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
    - Olds, Irving S., 1954, 1957, 1960 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10)
      Concerns two articles written by Olds.
    - P and Q. General, 1949-1954 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
      Principal correspondents include John Marshall Phillips.
    - R. General, 1949-1954 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    - Romig, Edgar F., 1944-1963 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
      Concerns various articles and book reviews by Romig.
    - S. General, 1946-1954 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. General (4 folders), 1939-1961 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15-18)
      The 19 Sawitzky folders include some material related to William's Carnegie-funded activities at N-YHS in the early 1940s, including an outline and some notes for the lecture he taught at N-YHS on early American painters for New York University's Institute of Fine Arts (IFA), his publication of a monograph on Matthew Pratt (1942), and his work on other monographs in the early-mid 1940s. Most of the material dates from after William's death in 1947 and concerns Susan Sawitzky's efforts to continue William's work toward publications concerning Ralph Earl, Reuben Moulthrop, Lawrence Kilbourn, Abraham Delanoy, Jr., and others. In addition to letters, the folders include photographs, negatives, reproduction permissions, manuscript drafts, and other matter. (See also the William Sawitzky papers in N-YHS's manuscript collection; that collection includes typescripts of Sawitzky's 1940s lectures at N-YHS, which refer to some extent to artworks and exhibitions at N-YHS.)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. General (2 folders), 1943-1954 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. Ralph Earl (5 folders), 1942-1951, Undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-7)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. Reuben Moulthrop (5 folders), 1947-1950, 1956 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-5)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. Matthew Pratt, 1939, 1942 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. Three New York Painters, 1942-1946, 1950-1952 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 7)
    - Sawitzky, William and Susan Clay. John Watson, 1951 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 8)
    - Strickland, J.E., 1952, 1956-1960, 1965 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
      Concerns the proposed publication of a 1794 journal by William Strickland.
    - Supreme Court of Judicature of the Province of New York (3 folders), 1948-1965 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2-4)
      Concerns Paul M. Hamlin and Charles E. Baker's three volume edition of the court's minutes. Includes some editorial correspondence, but most concerns enlisting book reviews and fulfilling orders.
    - T. General, 1952-1954 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5)
    - Taylor, Walter A., 1961, 1964 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 6)
      Concerns requests of Taylor for book reviews.
    - Tolman, Ruel P. (2 folders), circa 1950s (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7-8)
      Includes photographs, color transparencies, transcripts of historic documents, and some notes related to Tolman's The Life and Works of Edward Greene Malbone, 1777-1807.
    - U, V, and W. General, 1947-1954 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
    - Westervelt, Leonidas, 1945-1950 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
      Concerns Westervelt's article "General Marion and the Sweet Potatoes" and various Jenny Lind collection-related matters.
    - White, Philip L., 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11)
    - Wright, Charles L., 1951-1956 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12)
      Concerns Wright's article "The Pioneer of Zinc Etching." Includes his early manuscript version.
    - Y. General, 1950, 1954 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
    - Zabriskie, George A., 1942, 1945-1954 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 14)
      Concerns various writings of Zabriskie and his editorial comments on the Quarterly. Also concerns Charles Baker's survey of Zabriskie's writings in 1945 and after his death in 1954. Includes two snapshots of Zabriskie from the late 1940s.
  - Subseries I.B. Dictionary of Artists in America Records, 1944-1982; 20.15 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged principally by format, with Groce's 1943 typescript opening the subseries, followed by correspondence, the inscribed book, and the note cards. The correspondence is arranged by correspondent, with the files of correspondence with George Groce first, followed by other correspondents in alphabetical order. These are followed by a small number of topical correspondence files.
    There are two sets of Groce correspondence files. The first set includes two folders of documents spanning the years 1945 to 1953 that were binder-clipped together in the original files and so were kept together as found. The second, and much larger, set are the principal, chronological files of Groce correspondence, spanning 1945 to 1956.
    The subseries includes two principal document types: correspondence from over ten years related to the production of the DAA and the note cards used during the research process to record information on artists, most of which were used for the entries in the DAA.
    The correspondence includes the extensive exchanges between the Washington, D.C.-based George Groce and the New York-based editors Charles Baker and David Wallace (who was also co-credited with Groce as an author). The DAA and specific artist entries are the principal subjects of the letters, but other subjects also appear at times, including other articles and book reviews by Groce, exhibitions, comments on the work of William Sawitzky and others in the field, and the like. The files of Groce's correspondence also include the originals, copies, or typescripts of letters sent to Groce or N-YHS by other correspondents and DAA contributors in connection with Groce's inquiries.
    The correspondence also includes files from a wide range of curators, editors, scholars, descendants of artists, and others providing information about artists for the DAA. Some correspondents also discuss their own interests or advance inquiries of tangential relevance to the DAA. Principal correspondents include J. Earl Arrington, Rudolf Berliner, Wolfgang Born, Ralph Catterall, David C. Duniway, Edward H. Dwight, Elliot A.P. Evans, Sinclair Hamilton, John Davis Hatch, Jr., Bertha L. Heilbron, H. Maxson Holloway, Cliff Lord, Wilbur D. Peat, Francis W. Robinson, Anna Rutledge, Robert Taft, and Edna T. Whitley.
    Finally, the correspondence includes exchanges between N-YHS and the publisher, Yale University Press, concerning arrangements for the production of the book and payment of royalties to N-YHS. These files include the original agreement with Yale concerning royalties and the records of royalties forwarded to N-YHS from 1959-1982.
    The subseries includes 19 boxes of note cards. All but one of these boxes appear to hold the original notes about artists developed by Groce and shipped to N-YHS. Several of the boxes are original and some have the shipping label on them. Paperclipped to many of the original note cards are added slips of paper with revisions, updated entry information, some correspondence, and other documents. Sixteen of the boxes relate to entries in the DAA and two boxes relate to artists that were "rejected" from inclusion. One box holds cards dating from shortly after the DAA's production and these record new information received in anticipation of a possible supplement to the DAA.
    The sub-series also includes a small number of topical files related to publicity and requests for copies of the DAA and a copy of the DAA inscribed by Groce to Baker.
    - Groce, George C. Typescript of expanded version of 1440 Early American Portrait Artists (5 folders), 1943 (Offsite-box 43, Folder 1-5)
    - Groce, George C. (Binder-clipped documents) (2 folders), 1945-1950, 1953 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Groce, George C. (Chronological files) (19 folders), 1945-1953 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3-21)
    - Groce, George C. (Chronological files) (2 folders), 1954-1956 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Other Correspondents. A-L (12 folders), 1944-1956 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 3-14)
    - Other Correspondents. M-Z (7 folders), 1944-1956 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-7)
    - Other Correspondents. Yale University Press (3 folders), 1952-1982 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8-10)
      Includes the agreement for royalty payments and the ensuing receipts (1959-82). Also includes 1952 correspondence with publisher Thomas Y. Crowell Company.
    - Publicity, 1944, 1956 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
    - Requests for the Publication, 1948-1956 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 12)
    - The New-York Historical Society's Dictionary of Artists in America, 1564-1860, 1957 (Offsite-box 63, Folder 1)
      Copy of the DAA inscribed by George Groce to Charles Baker. A few of the entries are lightly annotated. This copy of the book was used to hold sheets dating from the 1970s and afterward that noted corrections and other possible revisions in the event a supplement or revised edition should be produced. These sheets were removed from the book and placed with similar material in Series II.B.
    - Note Cards. Aamond - Behan [Behrens], 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 44, Cards -)
      This and the following 15 boxes (Aamond to Zimmer) include the notes on artists used by Groce and Wallace for entries appearing in the Dictionary of Artists in America.
    - Note Cards. Biegel [Beigel] - Breflchl?, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 45, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Brehan - Cave, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 46, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Cazenova - Cuypers, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 47, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Dacre - Eiseman, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 48, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Elder - Geyer, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 49, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Giampaoli - Hazlitt, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 50, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Head - Jay, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 51, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Jeanneret - Le Roy, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 52, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Le Serrurier - Melrose, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 53, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Menchilli - Ozanne, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 54, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Pabodie - Reinke, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 55, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Reisner - Sherwood, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 56, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Sheys - Symon, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 57, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Taber - Ward, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 58, Cards -)
    - Note Cards. Wardell - Zimmer, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 59, Cards -)
    - Note Cards for Entries Not Used in the Dictionary. Ahlborn Jayne, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 60, Cards -)
      This box and the next one include Groce and Wallace's notes on artists that did not receive entries in the Dictionary of Artists in America.
    - Note Cards for Entries Not Used in the Dictionary. Jeffers - Yvon (and a few misc.), 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 61, Cards -)
      The "few misc" cards in the box label refers to several cards that are out of alphabetical order and are found after Yvon.
    - Note Cards. Some for Included Entries and Some for Excluded Entries. Abbott - Zieber, circa 1956-1961 (Offsite-box 62, Cards -)
      This box appears to include notes on artists recorded in anticipation of a possible supplement to the Dictionary of Artists in America. The cards include both artists with entries in the DAA and those without entries.
  - Subseries I.C. David H. Wallace Papers, 1950-1958, 2009; 0.1 Linear feet
    Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
    The documents in this subseries were donated to N-YHS on November 9, 2015, by David H. Wallace, former Assistant Editor at N-YHS (1952-1956) and co-author of the Dictionary of Artists in America.
    The subseries includes documents created or compiled by David H. Wallace, Assistant Editor at N-YHS from September 1952 to December 1956. A major responsibility of Wallace's during his tenure at N-YHS concerned the New-York Historical Society's Dictionary of Artists in America, 1564-1860, which was published in 1957 and for which he was credited as co-author with George C. Groce. Wallace's papers include two transcripts he prepared in 2009 that include extracts from a diary he maintained and other documents from the 1950s. One of these transcripts recounts Wallace's day-day involvement with the DAA and the other provides a view of Wallace's overall activities at N-YHS, as well as his perspective as an N-YHS staff member in the early 1950s. The papers include a few letters, including those of 1952 from Director R.W.G. Vail leading to Wallace's employment, a 1953 letter from Louise Hall Tharp, and a 1958 letter from Wallace's successor as Assistant Editor. The subseries includes three photographs of N-YHS staff, including Charles Baker and Wallace, and publicity ephemera for the Bella Landauer collection, with a poem by Wallace.
    - Transmittal Documents, 2015 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 13)
    - Transcript re: Producing the Dictionary of Artists in America, 1952-1957, 2009 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 14)
    - Transcript re: N-YHS Experiences, 1950-1957 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1953, 1958 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 16)
    - Photographs; Landauer Ephemera, 1953, circa 1956 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 17)
- Series II. Publications (1960s-1980)., 1940s-1998 (bulk 1963-1979); 6.25 Linear feet
  The Publications, 1960s-1980s series includes the Editorial Department files primarily in relation to the production of the Quarterly from the mid-1960s to 1980. Many of these files include correspondence with the authors of articles for the Quarterly, and these files commonly include the author's original submission, the editor's comments, commentary from the N-YHS Publications Committee, and galley proofs. The series also includes correspondence concerning the design and printing of the Quarterly, production expense budget data, work files with edited copy of book reviews for the Quarterly and of the N-YHS Annual Report, and other matter.
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  II.A. Correspondence by Author
  II.B. Other Correspondence and Work Files
  - Subseries II.A. Correspondence by Author, 1957-1980; 3.33 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged in alphabetical order, by author. The folder labels also include the shorthand article reference included on the original labels.
    The Correspondence by Author subseries includes correspondence between the N-YHS Editorial Department and the authors of, primarily, articles for the N-YHS Quarterly. The bulk of the material relates to published articles, with a few exceptions for unpublished matter. The correspondence concerns the communication of edits to the author, transmittals of various versions of the article, and obtaining permissions for image reproductions. Most of these are straightforward exchanges leading to the final, polished product, but others reflect a more intense editing process and some editor/author friction.
    Most of the folders include the galley proofs with author edits noted. Many folders include the initial or edited manuscript submission, with annotations, and those folders that include the manuscript are noted in the container list. Many of the folders also include the informal notes with commentary exchanged between the Editorial Department, Director James Heslin, and the Publication Committee regarding whether to publish the article, its importance, suitability for the Quarterly, quality of the author's argument and writing, and need for edits. A small number of folders include reader reactions to the article.
    - Aldridge, A. Owen. "Thomas Paine and New York Newspapers", 1975 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1)
    - Anderson, Samuel K. "Colonial Lotteries", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 2)
      Includes manuscript submission "Public Lotteries in Colonial New York."
    - Ashton, Rick J. "New York Congressmen", 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Loyalist Congressmen of New York."
    - Barlow, William. "Jonathan Fisk", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
      Includes manuscript submission "Jonathan Fisk and the Relocation of the Nation's Capital."
    - Bourne, Kenneth. "Chas. Hamilton Smith", 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission "Mr. Smith: An Early Honorary Member."
    - Boyer, Lee A. "Lobster Backs", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 6)
    - Buenker John D. "Progressivism in Practice", 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 7)
      Includes manuscript submission "Progressivism in Practice: New York State and the Federal Income Tax Amendment."
    - Buranelli, Vincent. "Colden", 1973 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 8)
      Concerns a proposal for a publication of the scientific papers of Cadwallader Colden.
    - Butscher, Edward. "New Netherland Negroes", 1971 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Negroes of New Amsterdam: Dutch Attitudes and Black Statistics."
    - Butterfield [Roger?]., Undated (Offsite-box 14, Folder 10)
      Includes a typescript of a journal, 1809-1819.
    - Calhoun, Richard B. "New York Fire Department", 1975 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 11)
      Includes manuscript submission "A Civil War Legacy: New York City Fire Department Reorganization, 1865-1870."
    - Carpenter, John A. "New York International Relief Committee", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "The New York International Relief Committee: A Chapter in the Diplomatic History of the Civil War."
    - Cave, Alfred A. "Colton", 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 13)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Case of Calvin Colton: White Racism in Northern Antislavery Thought."
    - Cerillo, Jr., Augustus. "Reform From Low", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 14)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Reform of Municipal Government in New York City: From Seth Low to John Purroy Mitchel."
    - Chalmers, Leonard. "Fernando Wood", 1968 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 15)
    - Chalmers, Leonard. "Tammany Hall", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 16)
      Includes manuscript submission "Tammany Hall, Fernando Wood, and the Struggle to Control New York City, 1857-1859."
    - Chalmers, Leonard. "La Guardia, 1973 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 17)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Crucial Test of Fiorello La Guardia's First Hundred Days: The Emergency Economy Bill."
    - Cohen, Ronald D. "Hartford Treaty", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Hartford Treaty of 1650: Anglo-Dutch Cooperation in the Seventeenth Century."
    - Cohen, Ronald D. "Recapture New Netherland", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)
      Includes manuscript submission "The New England Colonies and the Dutch Recapture of New York, 1673-1674: A Case of Colonial Particularism."
    - Cohen, Sheldon. "Elias Neau", 1968, 1970 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 3)
      Includes manuscript submission "Elias Neau: Humanitarian Catechist."
    - Cox, Richard. "Coney Island", 1975 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 4)
      Includes manuscript submission "Coney Island as Urban Symbol in American Art."
    - Curran, Thomas J. "Seward & Know Nothings", 1966 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission "Seward and the Know-Nothings."
    - Curran, Thomas J. "Van der Lyn", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 6)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Diary of Henry Van der Lyn."
    - Dana, Nathalie. "Municipal Art Society", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 7)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Municipal Art Society: Seventy-Five Years of Service to New York."
    - Davisson, William I. "Bradley-Maritime New York", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 8)
      Includes manuscript submission "New York Maritime Industry: Ship Voyage Patterns."
    - De Jong, Gerald F. "Megapolensis", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission "Dominie Johannes Megapolensis: Minister to New Netherland."
    - De Jong, Gerald F. "Ziekentroosters", 1970 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 10)
    - Delp, Robert W. "Andrew Jackson Davis", 1971 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 11)
      Includes manuscript submission "Andrew Jackson Davis's Revelations: Harbinger of American Spiritualism."
    - D'Innocenzo, Michael. "Stamp Act", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Role of the New York Newspapers in the Stamp Act Crisis, 1764-66."
    - Dobson, John M. "George William Curtis", 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 13)
      Includes manuscript submission "George William Curtis and the Election of 1884: The Dilemma of the New York Mugwumps."
    - Downey, Matthew T. "Cleveland & Hewitt", 1970 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 14)
      Includes manuscript submission "Grover Cleveland and Abram S. Hewitt: The Limits of Factional Consensus."
    - Dunnings, Jr., Thomas J. "Minutes of Oceanus Engine Co.", 1969 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 15)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Minutes of Oceanus Engine Company No. 11, 1780-1819."
    - Egan, Clifford L. "David Bailie Warden", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1)
      Includes manuscript submission "David Bailie Warden's Of the Probable Duration of the American Government."
    - Fehl, Philipp. "Washington's Canova", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 2)
      Includes manuscript submission "John Trumbull and Robert Ball Hughes's Restoration of the Statue of Pitt the Elder."
    - Fowler, Jr., William M. "Yankee Peddler", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 3)
      Includes manuscript submission "A Yankee Peddler, Non-Importation, and the New York Merchants."
    - Gahn, J. Anthony. "William Gropper", 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 4)
      Includes manuscript submission "William Gropper in New York: The Early Career of a Radical Cartoonist, 1897-1928."
    - Gerlach, Don R. "Schuyler", 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission "Philip Schuyler and the New York Frontier in 1781: Leading and Misleading the Enemy."
    - Glassie, Henry H. "Thomas Cole, Etc.", 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 6)
    - Hanyan, Craig. "Clinton", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7)